A Guide to the Additional Papers of Dumas Malone 1913-1986
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- Research Files for Jefferson and His Time
  - Thomas Jefferson
    - Monticello--Furnishings 1949-1979, & n.d. (Box 55)
    - Monticello--Grounds 1978 & n.d. (Box 55)
    - Monticello--Grove Restoration 1977 (Box 56)
    - Moticello--Land 1979-1981 (Box 56)
    - Monticello--After Death of Jefferson 1956, 1976, & n.d. (Box 56)
    - Mould Board for Jefferson Plow 1947 & n.d. (Box 56)
    - Music 1943-1976, & n.d. (Box 56)
    - Palladian Architecture in Italy ca. 1959 & n.d. (Box 56)
    - Papers of Thomas Jefferson ---Control Film 1956 (Box 56)
    - Philosophy--Attitude Towards Public Office n.d. (Box 56)
    - Philosophy 1961-1962, & n.d. (Box 56)
    - Philosophy--General and Political 1940-1976, & n.d., 3 folders (Box 57)
    - Politics, Practice of n.d. (Box 57)
    - Poplar Forest 1946-1972, & n.d. (Box 57)
    - Portraits and Statues 1943-1960 (Box 57)
    - Printed Material 1948-1964 (Box 57)
    - Religion - Jefferson Bible, etc. 1976-1979 (Box 57)
    - Science--American Philosophical Society n.d. (Box 57)
    - Science - General 1916-1978, & n.d. (Box 57)
    - Science--Medicine ca. 1936-1978 (Box 58)
    - Science--Societies 1971 & n.d. (Box 58)
    - Seal--The Great Seal of Virginia 1976 & n.d. (Box 58)
    - Slavery & Negroes, including Sally Hemings Affair 1943-1978, & n.d., 3 folders (Box 58)
    - Visitors to Monticello n.d. (Box 58)
    - Washington, City of n.d. (Box 58)
    - Wine and Food 1975-1976 (Box 58)
    - Writing n.d. (Box 58)
    - Young Men Associated with Thomas Jefferson 1947-1957, & n.d. (Box 58)
- Miscellaneous Materials re Jefferson and His Time
  - American Book Awards - Vol. VI 1981-1982 (Box 59)
  - Appendices (Unused) - Vol. V n.d. (Box 59)
  - Bibliography - Vol. IV n.d., 59 (Box b)
  - Chapter Titles 1966-1981 (Box 59)
  - Clippings and Related Material - Vol. VI 1981-1982 (Box 59)
  - Correspondence - Vol. I 1946-1950, 3 folders (Box 59)
  - Correspondence - Vol. III 1959-1967, 2 folders (Box 60)
  - Correspondence - Vol. IV 1953-1972, 2 folders (Box 60)
  - Correspondence - Vol. V 1974-1975 (Box 60)
  - Correspondence -- Vol. VI 1981-1982, 2 folders (Box 60)
  - Covers 1983 (Box 61)
  - Errata - Vol. IV-VI 1970-1982 (Box 61)
  - Final Drafts - Vol. VI (Miscellaneous Chapters) 1976-1977 (Box 61)
  - First Drafts - Vol. VI (Miscellaneous Chapters) n.d., 2 folders (Box 61)
  - Front Matter -- Vol. V 1973 (Box 61)
  - Illustrations (Not Used) ca. 1945-1981 (Box 61)
  - Illustrations - Vol. II 1949 & n.d. (Box 61)
  - Illustrations -- Vol. V 1978 (Box 61)
  - Illustrations -- Vol. I & II (Correspondence) 1944-1951 (Box 61)
  - Illustrations -- Vol. III, IV, V, VI 1962-1980, Correspondence, 5 folders (Box 62)
  - Index - Vol. V n.d. (Box 62)
  - Introduction - Vol. VI 1978, 2 folders (Box 62)
  - List for Complimentary Copies -- Vol. II 1948-1951 (Box 62)
  - Maps -- Vol. V 1969-1972 (Box 62)
  - Miscellaneous Notes n.d. (Box 63)
  - Record Book -- Vol. I-III 1947-1958 (Box 63)
    re Malone's Progress
  - Review -- Vol. I-VI 1948-1982, 6 folders (Box 63)
  - "Select Critical Bibliography" -- Vol. III n.d. (Box 63)
  - Symbols & Short Titles Used in Footnotes 1972-1979 (Box 63)
- Cassette & Video Recordings and Microfilm
  - Tape Recordings of the Chapters of Jefferson and His Time, Volume Six
    - "The Return of a Native" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "Presidential Aftermath, 1809-1811" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "Assets and Liabilities, 1809-1812" & Appendix n.d. (Box 64)
    - "The Young Gardner" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "The Batture Controversy, 1807-1814" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "Patriotism at Home, 1810-1812" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "Renewing Old Friendship" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "The Impact of War" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "The Meaning of Peace" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "The Political Economy of a Country Gentleman" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "The Monticello Circle" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "Books in Transit: The Library of Congress" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "The Ways of a Humanist" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "The Uses of History" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "Keeping the Record Straight" (Part I) n.d. (Box 64)
    - "Keeping the Record Straight" (Part II) n.d. (Box 64)
    - "Education Aspirations, 1779-1814" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "From Academy to College, 1814-1816" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "The Start of an Academical Village, 1816-1817" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "Winning a Charter, 1817-1819" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "The Solicitous Grandfather" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "The Harrassments of Debt, 1817-1822" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "The Hope and Fear of a Slaveholder" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "Fireball in the Night: The Missouri Question" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "Republicanism, Consolidation, and States' Rights" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "Foundations and Frustrations: The University, 1819-1821" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "The Empty Village, 1820-1824" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "A Bold Mission and a Memorable Visit" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "Life Comes to the University, 1825" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "A Last Look at Public Affairs" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "The Changing Family Scene" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "A Troubled Twilight" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "The End of the Day" n.d. (Box 64)
    - "Introduction" and the Appendix,"The Hemings Family" n.d. (Box 64)
  - Tape Recordings re Jefferson and Education
    - Education Chronology 1760-1818 Nov, Tape 1-8 (Box 64)
    - Central College 1816-1818 Oct, Tape 9-12 (Box 64)
    - Central College & Education Chronology 1818 Oct- 1819 Jan, Tapes 13-14 (Box 64)
    - Education Chronology 1819 Jan, Tape 15 (Box 64)
    - The University of Virginia 1819 Jan - 1822 Mar, Tapes 16-22 (Box 64)
    - The University of Virginia 1822 Mar- 1826 Jun, Tapes 23-38 (Box 65)
    - The Context of the University -- Supplement n.d., Tape 39 (Box 65)
  - Miscellaneous Jefferson Research Tapes
    - Republicanism 1816 Feb -1825 Dec, Tape 1-6 (Box 65)
    - Republicanism, Supporting Material n.d., Tapes 7-8 (Box 65)
    - Consolidation n.d., Tape 9-10 (Box 65)
    - State Rights -- Background n.d., Tape 11 (Box 65)
    - Anas n.d., Tape 14 (Box 65)
    - Thomas Jefferson Portraiture, Religion n.d., Tape 15 (Box 65)
    - Introduction to the Life and Morals of Jesus n.d., Tape 16 (Box 65)
    - "The Declaration of Independence" n.d., Tape 17 (Box 65)
    - Virginia Constitutional Reform n.d., Tape 18 (Box 65)
    - Changing Family Scene - Eppes & Randolph n.d., Tape 19 (Box 65)
    - Changing Family Scene -- Randolph, Trist, Coolidge n.d., Tape 20 (Box 65)
    - Changing Family Scene - Coolidge n.d., Tape 21 (Box 65)
    - Recommendation of Bernard Peyton for Postmaster of Richmond n.d., Tape 22 (Box 65)
    - Jefferson and Slavery n.d., Tapes 23-27 (Box 65)
    - The Missouri Controversy n.d., Tape 28-31 (Box 65)
    - Dr. Robley Dunglison Letters n.d., Tape 32 (Box 65)
    - Thomas Jefferson & William Wirt n.d., Tape 33-35 (Box 65)
      re Patrick Henry
    - John Adams and Thomas Jefferson Correspondence n.d., Tapes 36-37 (Box 65)
    - Foreign Affairs and the Monroe Doctrine n.d., Tape 38-39 (Box 65)
    - National & International Affairs 1815-1826, Tape 40 (Box 66)
    - The Election of 1824 n.d., Tape 41-43 (Box 66)
    - Additional Family Material n.d., Tapes 44-45 (Box 66)
    - Ellen W. Coolidge & T. Jefferson Correspondence n.d., Tapes 46-47 (Box 66)
    - Ellen and Joseph n.d., Tape 48 (Box 66)
    - Letterbook of Ellen W. Coolidge at the University of Virginia n.d., Tape 49-50 (Box 66)
    - Jefferson's Travels, Carriage, etc n.d., Tape 51 (Box 66)
    - Merrill Peterson n.d., Tapes 52-53 (Box 66)
      re the University of Virginia
    - Charles Lewis Bankhead's Conflict with Thomas Jefferson Randolph n.d., Tape 54 (Box 66)
    - Jefferson Letters in the Henry E. Huntington Library 1809-1826, Tape 55-57 (Box 66)
    - Revisional Material for Chapter 19, "Winning a Charter" n.d., Tape 58 (Box 66)
    - Helen Cripe's Thomas Jefferson and Musicn.d., Tape 59 (Box 66)
    - Lands of the University n.d., Tape 60 (Box 66)
    - Land and Buildings of the University of Virginia n.d., Tape 61 (Box 66)
    - Proposals for Systems of Public Education 1815-1819, Tape 62 (Box 66)
    - The Virginia State Legislature & Education 1809-1817, Tape 63 (Box 66)
    - Miscellaneous Information from Randall's Biography n.d., Tape 64 (Box 66)
    - James B. Conant's Thomas Jefferson and the Development of American Public Educationn.d., Tape 65 (Box 66)
    - Samuel Knox, Central College and Legislative Actions 1816-1818, Tape 66 (Box 66)
    - Visitors to Monticello n.d., Tape 67 (Box 66)
    - Jane Hollins Nicholas and Thomas Jefferson n.d., Tape 68 (Box 66)
    - Public Affairs 1812-1826, Tape 69 (Box 66)
    - Architecture, Land, & Buildings of the University n.d., Tapes 70-71 (Box 66)
    - Ablemarle County Historical Society Magazine Articles n.d., Tape 72 (Box 64)
      re the Architecture of the University
    - The Buildings of the University -- Supplementary Tape n.d., Tape 73 (Box 66)
    - Jefferson's Last Days n.d., Tape 74 (Box 66)
    - Bible Time-Line by Dayis Muth for the Boston Christian Science Center Exhibit n.d., Tape 75 (Box 66)
  - Video Cassette Recordings
    - "Dumas Malone: A Journey With Mr. Jefferson" n.d. (Box 66)
    - "Jefferson Scholar" Interview of Dumas Malone by Mr. Shepard of ABC News 1982 Mar 7 (Box 66)
  - Microfilm
    - "Responsibility and Privacy: Mr. Jefferson and the Press, 1798-1826" n.d. (Box 66)
    - The Papers of Thomas Jefferson Transcripts n.d. (Box 66)
- Research Notecards
  - Notecards 1792-1793
  - Notecards 1794-1800
  - Notecards 1800-1803
  - Notecards 1803-1805
  - Notecards 1805-1807
  - Notecards 1807-1808
  - Notecards (Miscellaneous) 1808-1826
  - Malone Bibliography/ General Bibliography/ Slavery n.d.
  - Bibliography/ Newspaper Notes n.d.
- Oversize
  - Photograph of Thomas Jefferson's Books 1968 (Folder 1)
  - Photographs n.d. (Folder 1)
    of Thomas Jefferson's Portraits, Houdon's Bust of Jefferson, Jefferson's Tombstone, Library at Monticello, Views of Monticello, Poplar Forest, Virginia State Capitol Building, and Secretary's Ford
  - Blueprint of Residence at 15 Pinehurst Road Suggested Alterations 1940 June 12 (Folder 2)
  - Massachusetts Historical Society Membership Certificate of Dumas Malone 1968 (Folder 2)
  - Honorary Citizen Certificate of New Orleans (for Dumas Malone) 1968 Nov 7 (Folder 2)
  - Portfolio of Portraits -- Mississppi Writers 1981 (Folder 2)
  - Projection of the first floor, Monticello n.d. (Folder 2)
  - University of Virginia Buildings & Ground Plan n.d., Printed (Folder 2)
  - Photostats of Continental Congress Records (1775-1776) Agreement of Secrecy & Resolution for Independence n.d. (Folder 2)
  - Photostats n.d. (Folder 3)
    Richmond Recorder articles re the Callender Scandals; the Joshua Fry-Peter Jefferson Map of Virginia & Maryland (1751); Embargo article (1807); and the United States Congress Proclamation (1784)
  - Map of the City of Washington, ca. 1801-1809, hand drawn (Folder 3)